A Guide to the Dr. Henry H. Presler Archives 1949-1989
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Dr. Henry H. Presler Archives 1949-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11208
ca. 350 items (53 Hollinger boxes and ca. 170 oversize items, ca. 40 linear shelf feet)
This collection consists of research materials, 1949-1989, ca. 350 items (53 Hollinger boxes and ca. 170 oversize items, ca. 40 linear shelf feet) including bound volumes, picture albums, maps and binders of computer print-outs, pertaining to basic case studies of ca. 4,010 religious institutions in Jabalpur, Madhya Pradesh, India and its immediate environs, conducted by Dr. Henry Hughes Presler, Fargo, North Dakota, and his associates. Dr. Presler received his education at the North Dakota State University (B.S.), the Boston University School of Theology (B.D.), and the University of Chicago (Ph.D.).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Dr. Henry H. Presler Archives were given to the University of Virginia Library by Marion C.A. Presler, Fargo, North Dakota, on October 18, 1995, and are unrestricted.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of research materials, 1949-1989, ca. 350 items (53 Hollinger boxes and ca. 170 oversize items, ca. 40 linear shelf feet) including bound volumes, picture albums, maps and binders of computer print-outs, pertaining to basic case studies of ca. 4,010 religious institutions in Jabalpur, Madhya Pradesh, India and its immediate environs, conducted by Dr. Henry Hughes Presler, Fargo, North Dakota, and his associates. Dr. Presler received his education at the North Dakota State University (B.S.), the Boston University School of Theology (B.D.), and the University of Chicago (Ph.D.).
The case studies were based on field work observations made since India's independence in the region of Jabalpur, in central India, a valley three miles wide and seven miles long, with the west end opening upon the Narmada River, one of India's seven sacred rivers. Dr. Presler, director of the Department of Organized Research (D.O.R.) supervised about 100 field workers, seven typists, and about 200 student helpers in this endeavor from 1949-1972. Each field worker attempted to describe and explain the religious institutions and practices in his own section. The case studies include much information valuable to the historian of Christianity, Islam, Sikhism, Jainism, Zoroastrianism, Hinduism, and Tribal religions in India.
The type of information included in each individual case study may include: "Geographical location, natural area, religion, sect, dimensions of structures, name of institution, functionaries, functions, income, daily rituals, festivals, constituency (single caste, mixed castes, social status, economic grade, formal education, language), management special week days, whether dead, deserted, or living property ownership, endowment if any, religious experiences (apparitions, ecstasy, cures, etc.), images (human form, animal form, stones), signs (colors, slogans, symbols, ornaments, astral, geological formations), sacred trees and shrubs, ritual accouterments (books, sounds, smokes, etc.), magic, evil eye, legends, myths, testimonies, stories, history, plus whatever respondents wanted to tell about their religion."
Dr. Presler organized and analyzed his data in ways most useful to quantitative sociologists of religion. In his research, Presler employed statistical analysis and emergent computer technology that has since become somewhat obsolete. A bound volume called by Presler the Key Book (found in Box 1 with his other guides to the collection), 762 pages, contains codes referring to locations on [computer] cards and electronic computer tapes and cassettes. To use the Key Book and the computer print-outs, the researcher should read Presler's pamphlet "Catalogue of Mid-India Field Research (gray binder), especially pages 10-22, which explain the contents of the binders of computer print-outs. In order for researchers to use this collection, they should consult Presler's own guides to this material located in Box 1 and should be allowed to keep Box 1 with them in the Reading Room while using other boxes from the collection.
Organization
The Archives follow the original arrangement by Presler into seven series:
I) Serially bound case studies, Department of Organized Research (D.O.R.) Reports (Boxes 1A-14)
II) Geographically arranged case studies D.O.R. Reports (Boxes 14-31)
III) Serially arranged picture albums D.O.R. Reports (Boxes 31-41)
IV) Bound Ward Summaries (Boxes 42-47)
V) Bound Coding Minutes (Boxes 48-52)
VI) Oversize computer print-outs and maps; and
VII) Oversize volumes of the Kanpur Analyses.
Contents List
- Series I: Serially Bound Case Studies Department of Organized Research (D.O.R.) 1949-1972, 1995 (Box 1-14)
  - Key Book and other guides produced by Presler for researchers using this collection 1968, 1995, 10 items (Box 1)
    Reading Room staff, please allow researchers to keep Box 1 for reference in the Reading Room as part of the guide and not a box of the collection.
  - D.O.R. Reports 1-599 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 1-A)
  - D.O.R. Reports 600-999 1949-1972, 4 volumes (Box 2)
  - D.O.R. Reports 1000-1399 1949-1972, 4 volumes (Box 3)
  - D.O.R. Reports 1400-1599 and 1700-1799 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 4)
    No sixteen hundreds exist
  - D.O.R. Reports 1800-2099 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 5)
  - D.O.R. Reports 2100-2399 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 6)
  - D.O.R. Reports 2400-2599 1949-1972, 2 volumes (Box 7)
  - D.O.R. Reports 2600-2799 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 8)
  - D.O.R. Reports 2800-2983 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 9)
    No three thousands exist in these volumes
  - D.O.R. Reports 4000-4149 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 10)
  - D.O.R. Reports 4150-4299 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 11)
  - D.O.R. Reports 4300-4450 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 12)
  - D.O.R. Reports 4451-4599 1949-1972, 13 volumes (Box 13)
  - D.O.R. Reports 4600-4649 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 14)
    Numbers 5000-5100 exist only on tape
- Series II: Geographically Arranged Case Studies Department of Organized Research (D.O.R.) Reports 1949-1972 (Box 14-31)
  - Inside the Municipality 1949-1972 (Box 14-29)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 1 Garha--Imarti Tank Section & South Triangle Section 1949-1972, 2 volumes (Box 14)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 1 Garha--Surjala Tank, Phulai Tank & North Triangle Sections 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 15)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 1 Garha--Southeast Section 1949-1972, 2 volumes (Box 16)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 2 Kachhipura--Northwest Section 1949-1972, 1 volumes (Box 16)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 2 Kachhipura--Northeast, Southwest & South Middle Sections 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 17)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 2 Kachhipura--Southeast Section 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 18)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 3 West Niwarganj--North & South Sections 1949-1972, 2 volumes (Box 18)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 4 East Niwarganj--Book 1 & Two 1949-1972, 2 volumes (Box 19)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 5 Cherital 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 19)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 6 Upreganj--Book One & Two 1949-1972, 2 volumes (Box 20)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 7 South Miloniganj 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 20)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 8 North Miloniganj 1949-1972, 1 volumes (Box 21)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 9 Gohalpur--Book One & Two 1949-1972, 2 volumes (Box 21)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 10 Motinala 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 22)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 11 Kotwali 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 22)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 12 Hanumantal 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 22)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 13 Sarafa 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 22)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 14 Lord Ganj 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 23)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 15 Wright Town 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 23)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 16 Marhatal 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 23)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 17 Omti 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 24)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 18 Bhartipur 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 24)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 19 Galgalia 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 24)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 20 Belbagh 1949-1972, 2 volumes (Box 25)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 21 Bhantaliaya 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 25)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 22 West Kariapathar 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 26)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 23 East Kariapathar 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 26)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 24 West Ghamapur 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 26)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 25 East Ghamapur 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 26)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 26 North Civil Station 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 27)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 27 South Civil Station 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 27)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 28 Napier Town 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 27)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 29 Gorakhpur 1949-1972, 2 volumes (Box 27)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Ward 30 Madan Mahal 1949-1972, 4 volumes (Box 28-29)
  - Outside the Municipality 1949-1972 (Box 29-31)
    - D.O.R. Reports: North of Kundam Road, Book One, Gokupur 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 29)
    - D.O.R. Reports: North of Kundam Road, Book Two, Khamaria Housing 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 29)
    - D.O.R. Reports: South of Kundam Road, GCF Estate 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 30)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Kanchanpura Area 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 30)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Saddar Area 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 30)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Cantonment Area 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 31)
    - D.O.R. Reports: Dectal, Kolatal, Pisanhari, and Mahapuri 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 31)
- Series III: Serially Arranged Picture Albums Department of Organized Research (D.O.R.) Reports 1949-1972 (Box 31-41)
  - Albums re D.O.R. Reports 1-199 1949-1972, 2 volumes (Box 31)
  - Albums re D.O.R. Reports 200-699 1949-1972, 5 volumes (Box 32)
  - Albums re D.O.R. Reports 700-1099 1949-1972, 4 volumes (Box 33)
  - Albums re D.O.R. Reports 1100-1499 1949-1972, 4 volumes (Box 34)
  - Albums re D.O.R. Reports 1500-2099 1949-1972, 5 volumes (Box 35)
    No sixteen hundreds exits
  - Albums re D.O.R. Reports 2500-2799 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 37)
  - Albums re D.O.R. Reports 2800-2893, 4000-4099 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 38)
    No three thousands exist in these albums
  - Albums re D.O.R. Reports 4100-4399 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 39)
  - Albums re D.O.R. Reports 4400-4599 1949-1972, 2 volumes (Box 40)
  - General Album I 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 40)
  - General Album II 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 41)
  - General Album III 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 41)
  - Unknown or Unidentified Pictures 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 41)
- Series IV: Bound Ward Summaries 1949-1972 (Box 42-47)
  - I. East of Corporation 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 42)
  - I.A 39 Deserted Villages 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 42)
  - II.A North Central Wards 22, 23, 24, 25 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 42)
  - II.B Northern and Northwest Ward 8 & 9 and Kanchanpura 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 43)
  - II.C Central Wards 7, 10, 21 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 43)
  - II.C Central Wards 13, 14, 17, 18, 19, 20 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 43)
  - II.D & E Outer Wards 3-5, 15 & 16, 23, 26-28 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 44)
  - II. Misecllanesous Wards, parts of 3, 4, 6, 9, 11-15, 18-20, 29, and more on Kanchanpura 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 44)
  - II.F Ward One 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 44)
  - II.F Ward Two and Supplements 1949-1972, 3 volumes (Box 45)
  - II.F Ward 30 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 46)
  - II.F Ward 30 Supplements, Ward 29, and Saddar 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 46)
  - The Gonds 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 46)
  - Jabalpur History 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 47)
  - Mid-India 1949-1972, 1 volume (Box 47)
- Series V: Bound Coding Minutes ca. 1957-1981 (Box 48-52)
  - Coding Minutes, Volumes A-C ca. 1957-1961, 3 volumes (Box 48)
  - Coding Minutes, Volumes D-G ca. 1958-1965, 4 volumes (Box 49)
  - Coding Minutes, Volumes H-J ca. 1961-1968, 3 volumes (Box 50)
  - Coding Minutes, Volumes K-M ca. 1961-1981, 3 volumes (Box 51)
  - Coding Minutes, Volume Q ca. 1961-1971 (Box 51)
  - Coding Minutes, Volumes N-P ca. 1961-1972, 3 volumes (Box 52)
- Gond Religion and Its Influence Upon Gond Institutions by Herman M. Reynolds n.d. (Box 53)
  A dissertation offered for a degree to Yale University, Department of Religion or Anthropology. Estimated to have been written around 1938-1940. xvi, 309 pages, illustrated with black and white photos, biblio, chart in pocket at back. The following is handwritten in ink on the inside cover: "Donated to the University of Virginia in memory of Herman M. Reynolds and Mildred Prichett Reynolds by their children Joyce Reynolds Coupal, Virginia M. Reynolds Nolan, Dr. Roger P. Reynolds. They were missionaries to India 1927-1959"
- Memories of India by the Reverend Herman M. Reynolds 1970 (Box 53)
- We Lived in Tiger Jungle by Mrs. (Mildred) Herman M. Reynolds n.d. (Box 53)
- Series VI: Oversize Computer Print-outs & Maps 1935-1989
  - Four printed maps of Jabalpur, India, used by Dr. Henry H. Presler 1947-1948 (Folder 1)
  - Ward maps on tracing paper for Jabalpur, India, including Wards 3, 4, 6, 8, 9, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26; the evacuated village of Manegaon; Vetla village; and cultural, land use & housing maps of Kanchanpura (41 sheets) and one large negative of Ward 27 1949-1954 (Folder 2)
  - Ward maps on tracing paper for Jabalpur, India, including Wards 5, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 21, 22, 24, 25, 26, 28, 29, 30; Sada; Karmata village; and a large map entitled "Jubbulpore Cantonment" (24 sheets) 1935-1936, 1949-1954 (Folder 3)
  - Negatives of the Ward Maps for Jabalpur, India (18 negative sheets) 1948-1952 (Folder 4)
  - Oversize Computer Print-out Bound Volumes 1971-1989
    Binder numbers refer to those numbers assigned by Presler to the computer print-out and written on the cover; for Presler's description see his gray pamphlet "Catalogue of Mid-India Field Research" pages 10-22.
    - Binder #100 1979-1980, Bound volume
      relates the kind of priest to the functions he performs using Discriminant Analysis
    - Binder #101 1980-1981, Bound volume
      discovers how the divinities cluster in small complexes using Factor Analysis
    - Binder #102 1980-1981, Bound volume
      Analysis of Variance re the relationship of socio-economic status to divinities and rituals
    - Binder #200 1980-1981, Bound volume
      Arrays of specific date on tribes, caste mohullas, divinities, etc. with percentages
    - Binder #201 1980-1981, Bound volume
      Arrays of Means or Averages on social status, economic grades, and education by divinities
    - Binder #300 1980-1981, Bound volume
      measures association of functionaries and their functions
    - Binder #301 1989, Bound volume
      explores questions related to cooperation vs. conflict between divinities, functionaries and laymen, and castes
    - Binder #400 1980-1981, Bound volume
      shows the divinities of all religions in the reports, labelled by each institution, with summaries
    - Binder #401 1980-1981, Bound volume
      for Signs only
    - Binder #402 1980-1981, Bound volume
      for Major and Minor Geographical Sections
    - Binder #403 1980-1981, Bound volume
      for Caste Mohullas
    - Binder #404 1980-1981, Bound volume
      for Natural Areas
    - Binder #405 1977-1981, Bound volume
      re Indices for Hindu D.O.R.'s Serialized
    - Binder #406 1980-1982, Bound volume
      re Indices for private, semi-private & public Hindu sites
    - Binder #407 1980-1982, Bound volume
      re Indices for all other religions than Hinduism, each separately
    - Binder #408 1980-1982, Bound volume
      Symbols Program for all 3596 Hindu D.O.R.'s, unrestricted
    - Binder #409 1981-1989, Bound volume
      Project XII pertaining to 4631 functionaries, 37 kinds, all religions
    - Binder #410 1981-1989, Bound volume
      Indices Program applies to gerographical sections (by ward)
    - Binder #411 1982-1989, Bound volume
      Symbols Program applied to geographical sections (by ward)
    - Binder #412 1974-1989, Bound volume
      contains copies of the many programs used on computer, itemwise
    - Binder #500 1980-1989, Bound volume
      examines functionaries using 3 approaches--Indices, Symbols & Labels
    - Binder #501 1980-1989, Bound volume
      examines Clean Shudras & their institutions using 3 approaches--Indices, Symbols & Labels
    - Binder #502 1981-1989, Bound volume
      examines Unclean Shudras & their institutions using 3 approaches--Indices, Symbols & Labels
    - Binder #503 1980-1989, Bound volume
      examines Scheduled Castes (Untouchables and Pariahs) & Tribals using 3 approaches--Indices, Symbols & Labels
    - Binder #600 1979-1982, Bound volume
      applies Indices program to each dimensional class (15 types) of worship buildings
    - Binder #601 1980-1982, Bound volume
      applies the Symbols program to each dimensional class of worship buildings
    - Binder #700 1978-1981, Bound volume
      Likelihood index for analysis of divinities' symbols
    - Binder #701 1976-1981, Bound volume
      applies comparison programs to specific divinities by site and caste
    - Binder #702 1976-1981, Bound volume
      five comparisons of divinities in Project XII
    - Binder #703 1979-1981, Bound volume
      shows which functionaries serve which divinities who are ranked according to spiritual hierarchy and actual usage hierarchy
    - Binder #704 1975-1981, Bound volume
      Presdata Tape Output
    - Binder #705 1979-1989, Bound volume
      re the goddess Khermai
    - Binder #706A 1975-1989, Bound volume
      applies Indices program to about three dozen divinities, kinds of religious experience, and forms of magic
    - Binder #706B 1981-1989, Bound volume
      applies Symbols program to five different divinities
    - Binder #900 1976-1981, Bound volume
      Individual Functions of functionaries
    - Binder #901 1976-1982, Bound volume
      relates functionary to chains of sits he serves, etc.
    - Binder #902 1977-1981, Bound volume
      shows how many kinds of functionaries normally perform this function
    - Binder #1000 1979-1980, Bound volume
      answers question "What kind of functionary do the various castes employ?"
    - Binder #1002 1978-1980, Bound volume
      answers question "What does a particular functionary do for a particular caste?"
    - Binder #1003 1979-1980, Bound volume
      answers question "What does a kind of fucntionary regard as proper and traditional functions for him to perform?"
    - Binder #1005 1975-1980, Bound volume
      uses Project XV only
    - Binder #1007 1980, Bound volume
      answers question "What kind of clients invite what kind of functionary to perform for them at the client's site or sacristy?"
    - Binder #1008 1976-1981, Bound volume
      answers question "What characteristics distinguish religious institutions with which professional functionaries are connected?"
    - Binder #1009 1980-1981, Bound volume
      a comparison program to show what each gropu is supposed to do as religious operatives
    - Binder #1010A 1982-1989, Bound volume
      roles played by functionaries
    - Binder #1010B 1983-1989, Bound volume
      roles played by functionaries continued
    - Binder #1011 1980-1989, Bound volume
      Symbols program run for sites with professionals only
    - Binder #1012 1980-1989, Bound volume
      Symbols Program run for sites with professionals only
    - Binder #1013.1 1980-1989, Bound volume
      explores what each functionary does at private, semi-private & public D.O.R. sites
    - Binder #1013.2 1980-1989, Bound volume
      applies the Indices program to the groups in Binder #1012 for comparison
    - Binder #1014A 1979-1989, Bound volume
      applies the Indices program and the Labels-Sums-9 Comparison program to D.O.R. sites as noted in Presler's catalogue
    - Binder #1014B 1981-1989, Bound volume
      Indices, Symbols, Labels-Sums Comparisons for Functionary 1, divinity 1, and caste 1 per site
    - Binder #1100 1980-1981, Bound volume
      explains how Presler recorded the Indices program, Symbols program, & Labels-Sums-10 Comparison program on computer tapes
    - Binder #1101 1974-1989, Bound volume
      records how Presler used Statistical Analysis System on some data
    - Binder #1102A 1985-1989, Bound volume
      Documentation for PRES 10 & 11
    - Binder #1103 1979-1989, Bound volume
      Library Listings
    - Binder #1104 1977-1978, Bound volume
      explains the logic and procedures for creating the D.O.R. library of data inputs on tape
    - Binder #1105 1975-1976, Bound volume
      listing of all Fortran and PL 1 programs used to prepare Presdata file of D.O.R. data
    - Binder #1200 1973-1981, Bound volume
      applies the Labels-Sums program to D.O.R. sites with 2-15 divinities per site
    - Binder #1201 1978-1981, Bound volume
      relates functionaries to their clienteles by traits of the latter
    - Binder #1300 1982-1989, Bound volume
      answers various questions re dimensional classes of sacristies using Jabalpur Valley data
    - Binder #1400A 1971-1989, Bound volume
      copies of the computer programs written by Presler, listed topically and chronologically
    - Binder #1400B 1974-1989, Bound volume
      copies of the computer programs written by Presler, listed topically and chronologically (continued)
- Series VII: Oversize Volume of the Kanpur Analyses ca. 1965-1966
  - The Kanpur Analyses, India Institute of Technology, Books A-U ca. 1965-1966, 21 bound volumes